Harry J. Marks Papers
© 2006 University of Connecticut
Harry J. Marks Papers.
undated,
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Marks, Harry J.
27.3 linear feet.
Papers of Harry J. Marks, long time professor of history at the University of Connecticut.
MSS19910031
Biography
Harry J. Marks was born 19 July 1909 in New York, NY. He received his education at Harvard University (A.B. 1931, Ph.D. 1937, A.M.T. 1946). He was hired as an instructor (History) by the University of Connecticut (Hartford campus) in 1946. A scholar of 19th and 20th century European social and intellectual history, Marks was promoted to Assistant Professor in 1947, Associate Professor in 1955, and Professor in 1963. The author of several books and articles, Marks was a member of the American Historical Association, American Association of University Professors and New England Historical Association. A professor in the John Hay Summer Institutes in the Humanities, Marks was also a visiting Professor of History at Connecticut College. Marks also did post-graduate work at the University of Heidelberg and the University of Berlin. He retired from teaching fulltime in 1978, but continued at the University until his death on 18 February 1988.
Scope and Content
Arrangement
Series I: Inventory ( undated, )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Marks, Harry J.
Organizations:
University of Connecticut--Curricula.
Places:
Storrs (Conn.); Europe--Social conditions--19th century.; Europe--Social conditions--20th century.; Europe--Intellectual life--19th century.; Europe--Intellectual life--20th century.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Notebooks.; Publications.; Photographs.; Color slides.; Blueprints.; Maps.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; Minutes.; Diaries.; Press releases.; Videocassettes.; Audio cassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Illustrations.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Typescripts.; Photocopies.; Notes.; Motion picture film.; Newspapers.
Occupations:
Educators.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Detailed Description
- Series I: Inventory, undated
  - Thesis: "Movements of Reform and Revolution in Germany from 1890-1903; with an Epilogue: from 1903-1914" [2 volumes], undated (Box 1)
  - Notes for thesis, filed by chapter, undated (Box 1)
  - Notes for thesis, filed by chapter; bibliographic material, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes for thesis, notecards filed by sub-topic, undated (Box 3)
  - History 258, 259 ["Part I"]: Lectures/notes/assignments filed by topic - notes also for The Pivotal Period in European History, undated (Box 4)
  - History 298, The Pivotal Period in European History: Notes organized by chapter, Correspondence with publishers and colleagues, undated, circa 1973 (Box 5-6)
  - The First Contest for Singapore:1819-1824: Footnotes, Elout (Bidgragen transcriptions of correspondence in Dutch, French), Correspondence with publishers/proofreaders, Notes, undated, 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Course files (Box 8)
    - Connecticut College - History 217/218, 1964-1965
    - History 225 - "European Intellectual History" - correspondence Roger Maren of The Reporter, Time, copy of Haveth Childers Everywhere by James Joyce, 1956-1964
    - History 229 - 20th Century European History, undated
    - History 258, "Opening Session" [graduate seminar], 1966-1983
    - History 325 [also contains History 217-218 materials] -- graduate seminar, selected topics, circa 1965-1971
  - Research Foundation Grant - 5.171-0-3-45-400-5-44, 1962 (Box 8)
  - "Since WWII: Arts" [contains New York Times clipping: Harold Schonberg's review of Karlheinz Stockhausen, 1971 (Box 8)
  - Assignments, hand-outs, notes and syllabi, undated (Box 10)
    - Education 202
    - Government 132 [international politics?]
    - Govt. 277 [Western governments?]
    - History 110 [ancient history]
    - Hist. 112 [modern history]
    - Hist 224 - "Europe in the 19th Century"
    - Hist 251 [Russian history]
    - Hist 259/Hist 324-25 [European history since 1815?]
    - Hist 301 [19th-century European history]
    - Hist 339 - "International Relations"
    - Hist 340-41 [Bibliography and Research Methods]
    - U.S. History [Amherst High School]
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 10)
  - Department/University matters, undated (Box 10)
  - "The Social Democratic Party of Germany, 1890-1914" [notes and manuscript], 1931 (Box 10)
  - Lectures/talks, undated, 1956-1977 (Box 10)
  - Course files, undated, 1948-1988 (Box 11)
    - History 100-01 [ancient history]
    - History 224
    - History 225 - "European Intellectual History"
    - History 229 [20th-century Europe]
    - History 258 [19th-century Europe]
    - History 259 [20th century Europe, "pivotal period"]
    - History 307 [19th-20th-century Europe]
    - History 324-25 [more "pivotal period"]
    - History 342 [historical methods?]
  - Lectures and talks, undated (Box 11)
  - Course materials, undated, 1974 (Box 12)
    - History 110
    - History 112
    - History 224
    - History 225
    - History 256
  - Academic, departmental and university materials, undated, 1970-1985 (Box 13)
  - Lectures and speeches, undated, 1972-1987 (Box 13)
  - Manuscripts, undated (Box 13)
  - Course materials, undated, 1952-1955 (Box 14)
    - History 251
    - History 319
    - History 340
    - History 342
  - John Hay Fellows, undated, 1962-1965 (Box 14)
  - Notes on Social History for "Chapter IX", undated (Box 15)
  - Publications by other authors, with notes, undated (Box 15)